# Kiprono Elijah Koech | Résumé

A Nairobi, Kenya

in: https://www.linkedin.com/in/kipronokoech

## Summary

Highly analytical, ingenious and results-oriented data scientist and statistician focusing on being a grounded researcher providing solutions to real-world problems through data analysis and modelling. Possessing working knowledge of Python programming and database management using SQL with the application in predictive modelling and data analysis, among other areas.

#### Key Skills

Areas of Expertise

**Applied Statistics** 

Machine Learning

Deep Learning

Computer Vision

Data Mining

Data Visualization

Reproducible Research

Business Intelligence and Analytics

Applied Mathematics

Database Management

Tools and Technologies.

Python | SQL |

SQL Git Version Control

R (familiar)

MEX

TensorFlow and Keras

AWS

HTML and CSS

Tableau Mic

Microsoft Office Suite

Docker SPSS

Linux

Soft skills...

Dependable

Very quick and eager to learn

Thriving in solving complex tasks

**Excellent Communicator** 

#### **Education**

Stellenbosch University

Certificate: Master's Degree in Applied Mathematics (Data Science)

Research area: Deep Learning/ Computer vision

Cape Town, South Africa

Feb 2020 - Apr 2022

Stellenbosch University

Certificate: Master's Degree in Mathematical Sciences, Cum Laude

Research area: Machine Learning and Computer Vision

Cape Town, South Africa

Jan 2019 - Nov 2019

Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology

Certificate: Bachelors Degree in Science (Statistics), First Class Honors

Nairobi, Kenya Sep 2013 – Nov 2017

## **Work Experience**

## Data Intelligence Analyst, SunKing Limited

A brief: Analyzing data to drive sales of our products.

Nairobi, Kenya January 2023 – To Date

- Design pilots, analyze data and make recommendations to improve sales
- Getting started, more to come...

## Data Science Intern, Kenya Meteorological Department

Nairobi, Kenya

A brief: Working on techniques to improve weather forecasting.

April 2022 – October 2022

- Working on improving weather forecasting through application of machine learning recurrent neural network models,
- Testing new parametrization schemes, and,
- Optimizing data assimilation procedures for Weather Research and Forecasting (WRF) model initialization.

#### Research Fellow, Science of Intelligence

Berlin, Germany

A brief: Worked on a computer vision project at Technische Universität Berlin.

Feb 2021 - Aug 2021

Worked on action recognition problem for wildlife

#### Data Science Technical Mentor, Great Learning - Olympus

(Remote) Texas, U.S.A *Nov 2020 – Aug 2021* 

A brief: A mentorship and tutoring role for data science students.

Mentored and tutored 6 students per semester taking a course in Data Science and Business Analytics at Olympus,

attaining 100% successful completion of the course.

#### Data Assistant, PACT-Timiza

Kisii and Migori, Kenya

A brief: Data entry, management and analysis role involving HIV patients information.

Jan 2018 - Dec 2018

- Managed HIV patients data for over 10,000 clients. This involved entering information on the paper into the IQ care database; analyze the data to locate clients with poor adherence and recommend follow-up; and data quality checks.
- Follow-up reduced the cases of poor adherence to anti-retroviral by over 70% and be able to close cases as required. Rectified an event that almost led to the loss of 2300 data points due to system failure. The by-product of this was setting up a more robust backup pipeline.
- Worked as a Data Clerk for the first 2 months then promoted to Data Assistant.

#### Statistician Intern, South Nyanza (SONY) Sugar Company

Migori, Kenya

A brief: An internship working with factory data in a sugar company.

Jun 2017 - Dec 2017

- Analyzed factory data to explain production trends and seasonality phenomena.
- Particularly analyzed downtime data and reported variables that are most significant in impacting the extent of downtime. Upon implementation, there was a 42% drop in downtime in 2018 compared to 2017.

#### **Projects**

- 1. Fruit Detection | Skills: Python, TensorFlow and Keras, Computer Vision
  - In this project, Mask R-CNN and YOLOv5 are deployed in context from fruit detection on outdoor images (apples and mangoes).
  - The two models achieved on-par state-of-the-art results attaining 93% and 88% F1 score for mango and apple images, respectively... more information in GitHub.
- 2. Reviews Classification | Skills: Web scraping, Sklearn, machine learning algorithms
  - $\circ$  This project involves scraping over 200k reviews using Scrapy and classifying them as positive or negative using different Sklearn models. Also, dealing with the issue of data imbalance.
  - SVM classifier was the best in this application achieving an F1 score of 89%... the code is in this GitHub repo.
- 3. Crop Disease Classification | Skills: Python, TensorFlow and Keras, Computer Vision
  - This is classification problem applied to Agriculture. This project was presented as a solution to a Zindi Challenge and ranked as top 15% solution...more information in GitHub.

#### **Award and Honors**

**Golden Key Award**, for being among the top 15% academic performers among the 2019 cohort. (2020-2022)

African Institute for Mathematical Sciences(AIMS) Scholarship, for MSc Mathematics at S.U (2019-2010)&(2020-2021)

**Award for Excellence**, African Institute for Mathematical Sciences(AIMS)

(Jan 2019- Nov 2019)

Vice-Chancellors Academic Award, the best student in Bachelor of Science (Statistics option)

(2014/2015, 2015/2016 and 2016/2017 academic years)

**First place**, Mathematics contest with 1954 contestants (2012)

# **Groups and Societies**

- Computer Vision and Remote Sensing Group at Technische Universität Berlin, Germany [1]
- Data Science Research Group at African Institute for Mathematical Sciences, South Africa [1]
- Golden Key International Honour Society
- Kenya National Society of Statisticians

## **X** Hobbies and Interests

- Volunteering and Charity work.
- Playing puzzle games like Rubik's cube and Sudoku game.
- Reading books. Currently reading "The Mountain is You" by Brianna Wiest

**Declaration**: I hereby declare that the information furnished above is true (*Thursday 9<sup>th</sup> February, 2023* at *14:14*).

Koch f

Kiprono Elijah Koech